<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the new creation. In a sermon preached at the head-quarters at Putney Sept. 29. 1647. By Thomas Collier.</title>
            <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1187_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867212</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867212</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169450</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169450)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 167:E1187[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the new creation. In a sermon preached at the head-quarters at Putney Sept. 29. 1647. By Thomas Collier.</title>
                  <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spred-Eagle at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LXV, 17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heaven --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169450:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THE <hi>New Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A Sermon Preached at the Head-Quarters at <hi>Putney</hi> Sept. 29. 1647.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Collier.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Pet. 3. 13.</bibl> 
               <hi>Nevertheleſſe we look for new Heavens, and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpred-Eagle at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169450:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169450:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE new Creation, the Kingdom of Heaven in the Saints, is that great Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie God is now revealing in them: I having both oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and freeneſſe, (at the head Quarters) ſpoke ſomething, according to that meaſure of light God hath communicated unto me, concerning this new Creation in the Saints; this truth being by ſome owned, yet by others privately oppoſed, and contradicted.</p>
            <p>I therefore at the deſire of ſome, who judge themſelves one with and in this truth; as alſo for ſatisfaction of the contrary mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have publiſhed that which was in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet in power then delivered: Although its true, thou maiſt not here reade <hi>verbatim</hi> what was then delivered, yet thou haſt here the heads and ſubſtance of it. God making thy ſpirit one in, &amp; with any truth that thou findeſt here, let him have the glory, and he who is thine, and the Truths ſervant hath his end, and utmoſt deſires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:169450:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169450:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Iſai. 65. 17.</bibl>
               <q>Behold, I create new heavens, and a new earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is a ſatisfying reaſon of ſome propheticall Goſpel-truths, formerly diſcovered. Wherein we may take notice, Firſt, of the grace of the Goſpel, verſe 1. <hi>I was found of them that ſought me not,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein you may note, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not ſeeking after grace, are made partakers of grace; or that perſons ſeek and finde grace, from their being ſought out and found by grace.</p>
            <p>Men participate of Goſpel grace, not becauſe there is either deſert or deſire in themſelves, but from the everlaſting love &amp; free bounty of a gratious God, who is the fountain of Grace and Love; ſee this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 3. <hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting love: therefore in loving</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169450:4"/> 
               <hi>kindeneſſe have I drawn thee.</hi> As this was a truth to the naturall <hi>Iſrael,</hi> much more is it a truth to the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Whence was it that God ſhewed mercy to <hi>Mary,</hi> out of whom was caſt ſeven Devils (that is, a perfection of wickedneſſe was in her) but Free-Grace and Love? ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 7. latter end, with Chap. 8. 2. with thoſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. who were the betrayers and murderers of Chriſt, made partakers of Grace by Chriſt. <hi>Saul, Acts</hi> 9. 1, 2, 3. who perſecuted Chriſt, received mercy by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. How might this incourage ſinners, yea, and the worſt of ſinners too, to expect not only the Declarations, but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of Grace from the Almighty? Haſt been a filthy polluted creature? ſo was <hi>Mary:</hi> haſt been an enemy to Chriſt, a perſecutor of chriſtians? ſo were thoſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Saul,</hi> Chap. 9. Yet he obtained mercy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 13, 14. And this is written for thy incouragement, that thou likewiſe maieſt expect mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. To raiſe up the ſpirits of Perſons made partakers of Grace, to admire God who is the fountain, and to cry Grace, Grace, unto it.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169450:4"/>
            <p> Secondly, here is the diſpoſition of man naturally, verſe 2. which is to oppoſe Grace; notwithſtanding, God ſpreads forth his hand unto them in the tenders of mercy, yet they walk after their own thoughts.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Goſpel-Truth by the Prophet diſcovered, is Gods exaltation of his own Name and People in the latter dayes, ver. 9. with the ruine of all enemies, both within them, and likewiſe without them: within them that ignorance and darkneſſe in the things of God, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalneſſe and fleſhlineſſe that naturally dwels in them, that unſatisfiedneſſe at all times and in all conditions, with the will of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all enemies without muſt be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually ſlain, verſe 12. See what the ſlaughter is, verſe 13. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold my ſervants ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be hungry: behold, my ſervants ſhall drinke, but ye ſhall be thirſty:</hi> that is, my ſervants who live in me, ſhall dwel on high. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 1. <hi>Bread ſhall be given them to eat, their waters ſhall be ſure, they ſhall feed on that feaſt made of fat things. Iſat.</hi> 25. which is, God in the ſpirit; when Formalliſts and Legalliſts, who live
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169450:5"/> on things without them, ſhall be hungry and thirſty, nothing to feed on, when the glorious appearance of truth, diſcovers the emptineſſe, and deſtroyes the beeing of that wherein they lived. Behold my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; behold, my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and howl for vexation of ſpirit; they ſhall be aſhamed, becauſe that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they truſted, their ſpirituall life and livelyhood, is taken from them: but ye (to wit the Saints who live in the ſpirit) ſhall rejoyce, ſhall ſing for joy of heart. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35. 10. <hi>Then ſhall the redeemed of the Lord return and come to Zion with ſongs and everlaſting joy upon their heads: they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſſe, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſighing ſhall flee away.</hi> This ſhall be, and is the life of Saints who live in the fountain, or rather in whom the fountain lives.</p>
            <p>In a word, theſe two things are here preſented, Firſt, The rejection, or rather the ſubjection under feet of the enemies of God. Secondly, The exaltation, glory and joy of the Saints. ver. 15. <hi>Ye ſhall leave your name for a curſe to my choſen:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169450:5"/> 
               <hi>for the Lord God will ſlay thee, and call his people by another name.</hi> That is, whereas the name <hi>(viz.)</hi> the power of the wicked hath been exceeding high, the Lord will ſlay that name, bring down their power and glory, and lay it in the duſt, make it a reproach: but he will call his ſervants by another name, whereas formerly they had a name of reproach, accounted the off-ſcouring of all things, a reproach and proverb amongſt men; and ſo that word of truth hath been verified, behold, I and the children whom God hath given me, are ſet for ſignes and wonders in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Oh beloved! How have the Saints been ſet for ſignes and wonders, even amongſt thoſe who pretend themſelves to be the Lords <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Its true, in this and other Nations called Chriſtian, it's looked upon as an exceeding contemptible thing, not to be a Chriſtian, to be a Heathen, an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, this is an evil thing: But 2. It's account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a far more contemptible thing, to be a Chriſtian indeed; not to be a Chriſtian in form &amp; profeſſion, is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptible thing, but to be a Chriſtian indeed, is a more contemptible thing; a ſad word indeed, and it behoves thoſe who are the cauſers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169450:6"/> of it to look about themſelves, for the leaders of my people cauſe them to erre, and God is now caſting reproach upon them, but he will call his people by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how ſhall this be effected may ſome ſay, it is exceeding unlikely; wickedneſſe prevailes both within and without, in high and low, it ſeemes to be very unlikely?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nay, ſaith the Lord, I will effect it, rather then this great work ſhall be left undone, I will make a new Creation. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I Create new heavens and a new earth.</hi> verſe 17.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ecce,</hi> behold, notes the excellency of the thing to be beheld.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctr.</hi> But the generall truth which I ſhall at preſent commend unto you, is this,</p>
            <p>That the great work which God hath to effect (in the world and in the Saints) in theſe latter dayes of the Goſpel, is to ſet up a new Creation, <hi>viz. New heavens and a new earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this truth, I ſhall firſt open the tearms unto you, what is meant by the new heavens and the new earth, in the unfolding of which. I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169450:6"/> ſhall confirme the truth propounded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the word Heaven it hath dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent acceptations in Scripture, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times its taken for the Aiery Firmament, in which the fowls flie; ſometimes for the Starry Firmament, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 8. Sometimes for the Preaching of the Goſpel, which is the word of the Kingdome yet called the Kingdome of Heaven, The Kingdome of Heaven ſhall be taken from you, &amp;c. Sometimes for the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 20. Sometimes for the Saints Union with God, and ſpirituall injoyment of him: now I underſtand Heaven in this place, according to the two laſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Saints with their injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in the ſpirit. It is true, there are different apprehenſions in many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Scripture; ſome apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it relates to the deſtruction of this materiall form and frame of heaven and earth, and the creation of a new, from that in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. Becauſe, ſay they, that the deſtruction of this materiall frame and form is only minded in that Chap. Now although I ſhall not deny that which is from hence concluded, yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that there is much myſterie in that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169450:7"/> Chapter; and ſhall be made good within the Saints in the Spirit, as well as without them according to the Letter, and that of the new heavens, is wholy myſticall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what light I have received, not that I deſire to argue forth the thing at preſent but with much tenderneſſe to paſſe it by.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſome apprehend, that Chriſt ſhall come and reign perſonally, ſubduing his enemies, and exalting his people, and that this is the new heaven and the new earth; but this is not my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: but that Chriſt will come in the Spirit, and have a glorious Kingdome in the ſpirits of his people, and they ſhall by the power of Chriſt in them, raign over the world, and this is the new heavens and the new earth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He will have a glorious Kingdom in the Saints, The kingdome of God is within you; heaven is the kingdome of God, and this kingdome is within the Saints, and this is the new Creation, the new heaven, the Kingdom of heaven that is in the Saints. It's true, we have had, and ſtill have exceeding low &amp; carnal thoughts of heaven, looking on it as a glorious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169450:7"/> place above the Firmament, out of ſight, and not to be injoyed till after this life: but God himſelfe is the Saints kingdome, their injoyment, their glory; where God is manifeſting himſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is his and the Saints kingdome, and that is in the Saints. Here lieth the great &amp; hidden myſterie of the Goſpel, this new creation in the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> Wherein lieth the nature and glory of this new Creation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The nature and glory of it lieth in that renovation or renewing of the minde: an internall and ſpirituall change, a transformation out of the nature of the firſt, into the nature of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> This I ſhall for your ſatisfaction, confirme unto you from Scripture, although I truſt I ſhall deliver nothing unto you but expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall truth. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>He that is in Chriſt, is a new Creature; old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new.</hi> Here is this new Creation within, a new creature, a minde renewed by the Spirit, this is that new man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mentioned <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 23, 24. which after God, is Created in righteouſneſſe and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; note, it is Created and that after God; now what this Creation or new
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169450:8"/> man is, according to what I underſtand, no farther I dare to ſpeak, it is that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Divine nature the Spirit, hath with and in our ſpirits, by which U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion it transforms our ſpirits into its own glory, and ſhall in concluſion, wholly ſwallow up the Saints in that ſpirituall glory, which will be their eternall perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, their heaven, their kingdom, their glory. This is the firſt part of both the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and glory of this new Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> Why is it called new heavens in this Scripture, as if it were ſome more then ordinary glory? this mentioned is that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God works ordinarily in every Saint, this new birth or ſpirituall renewing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It's true, that this new ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall work of God in the ſpirits of men is effected in the ſpirit of every Chriſtian, but this new Creation minded in my Text, is a more then ordinary degree of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall glory; for I do not underſtand by the new heavens, a new thing contrary to what hath been formerly, but a higher meaſure or manifeſtation of one and the ſame glory: as the covenant of grace was called a new covenant, not becauſe it was not in being formerly, but becauſe it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169450:8"/> ſhould be more gloriouſly manifeſted then formerly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſhould bring forth more glorious effects in the Saints then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>For my more cleare proceeding in, and your better underſtanding of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this new Creation, I ſhould minde one thing unto you by the way, and that is this,</p>
            <p>I minde the diſpenſations of God to the world, or rather the Saints in the world, to be anſwerable to his diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſpirit of every Saint, I minde it thus:</p>
            <p>That as God proceeds gradually in the manifeſting of himſelf in the ſpirits of his people, the firſt, ſecond, and third hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. or children, yong men, old men, as <hi>John</hi> hath it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ſo he makes known himſelf unto his Saints in the world, gradually, the firſt, ſecond, and third heaven, or diſpenſation of heavenly light and glory, or rather a different manifeſtation of one and the ſame diſpenſation of light and glory.</p>
            <p>As firſt, in the times of the Law, God made himſelf known to his people under dark ſhadows, and types; there was a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169450:9"/> glory, but it was ſuch a glory which made them exceedingly to quake and tremble.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the dayes Chriſt, who put an end to thoſe ſhadows, there was a higher manifeſtation of light and glory, wherein was more clearneſſe of light and joy, which was the yong, or middle age.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, in this laſt time, or third diſpenſation of God to, and in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, will be much more glorious, much more in the ſpirit, and therefore called a new heaven; it ſhall be the light of the ſame diſpenſation began in the Law, ſee this confirmed <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> Wherein doth the glory of this new heaven conſiſt more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, in the abundance of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>The knowledge of God ſhall cover the face of the earth, as the waters co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſea,</hi> you may reade from <hi>ver.</hi> 6. That the Lion and the Lamb, &amp;c. ſhall lie down together: I ſhall declare by the way what I underſtand to be the truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, not that I limit it from any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truth that any may ſee in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are all theſe things within us
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169450:9"/> in that old Creation, the Lion, and the Woolf, &amp;c. which oppoſes and prevents the Saints joy, and ſpirituall enjoyment of God; now theſe ſhall be ſo over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the glorious appearances of light, that they ſhall no more hurt, or deſtroy the Saints peace in their holy mountain, their enjoyment of God in the Spirit, which is the Saints mountain; for the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of God; the glorious appearings of light in the ſpirits of Chriſtians will ſo cover that earth which is within them, that they ſhall be in a great meaſure freed from thoſe corruptions, thoſe diſtractions which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly were prevalent in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God will take away the nature of wicked men, that although they remain Wolves, Lions, and brutes ſtill, yet they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all the holy mountain of God, that is, the Church; and that through the abundance of light that ſhall be communicated, even unto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men; for the earth, that is, earthly men muſt give glory to the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 14. The knowledge of the Lord ſhall cover the face of the earth, as the waters cover the ſea, for the earth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169450:10"/> ſhall be filled with the knowledge of the glory of God: there ſhall not be only the knowledge of God, that there is a God, but the knowledge of his glory ſhall be much more abundantly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, that herein lyeth one principall part of the glory of this new Creation, in the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>As ignorance is the grand cauſe of ſo much corruption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo many miſtakes in the things of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for alwaies the will and affection follows the underſtanding, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inlightned or blinded; ſo it is the knowledg of God, the breakings forth of light in the ſpirit, that delivers ſouls from that corruption and darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>This truth <hi>Paul</hi> manifeſts in his prayer for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Chap. 1. 17, 18. in his deſire for himſelf, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>That I might know him, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> Wherein ſhall the knowledge of the Saints increaſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Amongſt many I ſhall inſtance in theſe particulars following,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the knowledge of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of God, and that as he is in them, for God is a myſterie; <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 2. And it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169450:10"/> is by the appearance of God in us, we come to know God who is a myſterie. The truth is that we have had, and ſtill have, low and carnall thoughts of God, judging him to be a God afar off, and not a God nigh at hand, this is that Antichriſt which denies Chriſt to be come in the fleſh; this is that myſterie of which we are exceeding ignorant, God manifeſt in the fleſh, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 16. we have had very narrow apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Chriſt, and the manifeſtation of the glory of Chriſt, limitting it to that one man, when the truth is, that Chriſt and all the Saints makes up but one Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. And God as truly manifeſts himſelf in the fleſh of all his, as he did in Chriſt, although the meaſure of that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation is different. This is a myſterie which God is revealing in the ſpirits of his people, and is indeed the glory of this new Creation; this being in ſome meaſure manifeſted in the ſpirits of chriſtians, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth in the ſecond place,</p>
            <p>Secondly, A knowledge of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall liberty in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Spirituall liberty and juſtification from all ſpirituall enemies, ſin, law, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; whatever oppoſes the ſouls
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169450:11"/> peace, in this new heaven its all done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 36. <hi>If the Son ſhal make you free, then you are free indeed.</hi> Saints ſhall now come to ſee that they are free indeed by Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 39 <hi>By him all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve are juſtified from all things, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of Moſes. Gal.</hi> 5. 1. Thus Saints ſhall know their liberty, and ſtand faſt in it too, <hi>For the Inhabitant ſhall not ſay I am ſick, they that dwell therein ſhall be forgiven their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity. Iſai.</hi> 33. laſt. That is, they ſhall live in the knowledge of their liberty from ſin, although formerly through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we have not ſo much looked after it. This hath been accounted the higheſt meaſure of Chriſtianity, to ſee our ſelves juſtified, to injoy the full aſſurance of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Chriſt; a deſire of Faith was a high meaſure of Faith, and well if the ſoul get aſſurance while it hath a beeing in this body, and thus many a pretious ſoul hath lived low under legall bondage through ignorance; whereas juſtification from ſin by Chriſt, is the firſt ſtep in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and that which gives us the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of children. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. 11, 12. <hi>I write unto you little children, becauſe your</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169450:11"/> 
               <hi>ſins are forgiven you for his names ſake.</hi> Perſons injoying the forgiveneſſe of ſin, are but little children, babes in the ſchool of Chriſt. Now this liberty from ſin is, that the Saints ſhall live fully in the knowledge of it, as likewiſe in the knowledge of their liberty from legall bondage, and ſo from legall actings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 2. which I paſſe in this place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the knowledge of their liberty from men, 1 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 7. 23. <hi>Ye are bought with a price, be ye not the ſervants of men?</hi> That is not to be ſubject to men in the things of God, in matters of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that belongs only to God himſelf, it is his proper peculiar right to rule in the ſpirits of his people, although its true that there hath been, and ſtill is, through ignorance, a principle in man, not only to uſurp authority to rule in and over the conſcience of others, but a principle in us alſo out of conſcience, to ſubmit to man in ſuch caſes, now God is diſcovering, and likewiſe delivering his people from this ſpirituall bondage unto men in the things of God, and that from the knowledge of their liberty in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a liberty in knowledge, 1
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169450:12"/> 
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>Ye have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the holy one and ye know all things:</hi> that is all things that the Spirit makes known. They are not tyed to other mens approbation, but walk in that light the Spirit makes known in them, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The glory of this new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſts in the Saints knowledge of their peace, and union with God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Peace, and that firſt, peace with God, this is injoyed by faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God.</hi> Every man naturally is at a diſtance from God, but by Ieſus Chriſt they come to injoy reconciliation.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, They injoy not only peace with God, but peace with the Saints; it is only the glorious light of this New Creation that will put an end to theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions amongſt Chriſtians, it is not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſteriall power, ſetting up Uniformity, but that one Spirit of light and truth that muſt bring the Saints into this unity; I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not, but many of you have read what <hi>Zephaniah</hi> writes, Chap. 3. 9. <hi>I will turn to the people a pure language, and they ſhall ſerve me with one conſent, or with one</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169450:12"/> 
               <hi>ſhoulder.</hi> This pure language is the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the ſpirit, and the truth is, that nothing elſe will be able to put an end to theſe diviſions but this ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, this new creation of God in the ſpirits of his people, and this is and ſhall be the glory of this heaven, unity, and peace amongſt Saints, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 13. <hi>The envy of Ephraim ſhall depart, and the adverſaries of Judah ſhall be cut off, Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im ſhall not envy Judah, neither ſhall Judah vex Ephraim.</hi> Whence is it that there is ſo much envy in the ſpirits of chriſtians, but from their fleſhlineſſe, vexing each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they ſhould rather be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort each to other? but this ſhall depart, &amp; be gone in this new Creation; this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, it ſhall be a kingdome of peace, not only internall with God, with the Saints, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 12. but,</p>
            <p>Secondly, With men, and amongſt men of the earth; this new creation will put an end to all thoſe wars and confuſions in the world. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 4.</p>
            <p>When once the Saints mountain comes to be eſtabliſhed in the top of all moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; when they ſhall live in God who is their mountain, this light and glory
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169450:13"/> ſhall go forth ſo far amongſt the wicked, as that they ſhall imbrace peace, it will put a period to wars and commotions that are amongſt the men of the earth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is the knowledge, not only of their peace with, but of their union in God: here ſtill lieth the great myſterie of the Goſpel, the Saints union in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the knowledge of it is exceeding glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that this is a truth, ſee <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 21. There is a union of ſpirits, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17. A union in the power, wiſdome, and glory of the Father, but I forbeare the inlarging of theſe at preſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The glory of this new Creation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not only in knowledge, but in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall injoyment likewiſe; there is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ſpirituall injoyment, it does not only ſee and know, but it injoyes what it ſees, it ſees liberty and peace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes it, and lives in it; it ſees God in the Spirit, and lives in him; it not only ſees a union, but injoyes a union, both in ſpirit, wiſdome, power and glory of the Father, &amp; thus Saints that live in that abundance of life that is in God. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 10. <hi>I am come that ye might have life, and that ye might have it more abundantly.</hi> O the abundance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169450:13"/> of ſpirituall injoyment, of ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, Saints in this heaven injoy; hence it is the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 23. <hi>All is yours, &amp;c.</hi> And truly friends if all be the Saints, when they ſee it and injoy it, it will be enough to fill them with joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and full of glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The glory of this new Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts not only in being delivered from legall and fleſhly actings, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lives in the power of heavenly and ſpirituall actings, and that firſt, to God in ſpirituall prayer and praiſings; but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, from God, not only in the whole converſation, but likewiſe in acts of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and juſtice unto men, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in preachings and praiſings, all ſhall be done in the wiſdome and power of the Spirit, that ſo grace may be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the hearers. This is the third part of the glory of this new Creation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed by thoſe who live in it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And finally, the glory of this new Creation brings forth joy and gladneſſe in the ſpirits of thoſe who live in it, perpetual ſinging of new ſongs of praiſe unto the Lord; ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 4. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 7. I ſhall inſtance more particularly <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 1.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169450:14"/> where you ſhall finde, after the fall of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, which is effected as well within us, as without us, there was a voice of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, ſaying, <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>For the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth:</hi> This is that will miniſter occaſion to ſouls to ſing praiſes, when they can ſay truly, The Lord God omnipotent reigneth, that is, reigneth over fleſh, and corruptions, and the powers of darkneſſe are vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſubdued, Chap. 15. 3. <hi>They ſing the ſong of Moſes the ſervant of the Lord;</hi> but who ſung this ſong? thoſe who had gone through this ſea of glaſſe, and gotten the victory over ſpirituall enemies, who had gone through this fiery ſea, and overcome, they ſing this ſong of <hi>Moſes;</hi> its called the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe when <hi>Moſes</hi> could look back, and ſee his enemies dead in the red ſea, then he could ſing; ſo when ſouls ſee themſelves ſpiritually delivered, all their ſpirituall enemies lie dead before them, then they can ſing; this is that new ſong mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 3. That none could learn but thoſe who were redeem'd from the earth; it is called a new ſong, in oppoſition to the old, carnall, and formall ſingings of the world, it is ſuch a ſong, that none can learn, but thoſe who are redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169450:14"/> from the earth; what is that? why it is to be delivered from that earthlineſſe, and fleſhlineſſe that poſſeſſeth ſouls: when once ſouls are delivered from this earth; as they ſhall in this new heaven, then they can ſing new ſongs, and not till then; ſee one Scripture in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, amongſt many, anſwering this truth, <hi>Zac.</hi> 8. 19. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, The faſt of the fourth moneth, and the faſt of the fift, and the faſt of the ſeventh, and the faſt of the tenth ſhall be to the houſe of Judah joy and gladneſſe, and chearfull feaſts: therefore love the truth and peace.</hi> This, its true, relates to the Jews in the Letter, concerning their Babyloniſh capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but it principally relates unto our comming forth of myſticall Babylon, as its clear in the verſes to the end of the Chapter; all thoſe dayes of faſtings ſhall be turned into dayes of feaſtings. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in the Goſpel, when the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees queried of Chriſt, what the reaſon was that <hi>Johns</hi> diſciples faſted, and Chriſts faſted not, his anſwer was, the children of the Bridegroom cannot faſt ſo long as the Bridegroom is with them, but the time will come, when the Bridegroom ſhall be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169450:15"/> taken away, and then ſhall they faſt: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, it is an argument that the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom hath been gone from us a long time, and that is the cauſe of thoſe faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and mournings, but when the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom is come, thoſe dayes of faſtings and mournings ſhall be ended, and ſhall be turned into feaſtings, and ſpirituall prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. This is that <hi>Paul</hi> mindes in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Teaching and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing one another in Pſalms, and Hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs.</hi> And truly, when we come into theſe new heavens, we ſhall then know what it is thus to teach one another. Thus amongſt many, have I branched forth theſe few particulars, wherein the nature and glory of this new heaven conſiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. As to diſcover the ignorance of thoſe who would retain men ſtill in the old heavens, under carnall and fleſhly forms, ſo</p>
            <p n="2">2. To incourage Saints, who have yet but low apprehenſions of this glory, to preſſe forwards, as <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3. forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe things which are behinde, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing forward to the mark, that is, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Chriſt, who is the mark, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169450:15"/> prize run for. It is a low and carnall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, for to ſet men a looking back after what once the ſoul injoyed, not that I ſhall deny, but that God may communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate comfort to ſouls in this low conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that this is the temper of a Goſpel ſpirit inlightned in the myſterie of truth, to ſee the greateſt glory to be before, and that darkneſſe which is behinde, and ſo it forgets that which is paſt, from the glory of that which is before; truly, a ſoul taught of God in this ſpirituall myſterie of the new Creation, cannot reſt it ſelf ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that is, ſo ſatisfied, as not to preſſe forward, ſhort of glory, of that perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he ſees in Chriſt; this is the end of all Goſpel miniſtrations, thereby to work up ſouls into that unity of faith, and knowledge of the ſon of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in it, it ſhall be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſpeak more externally, by new heavens I underſtand to be meant, a new Church eſtate, and that in oppoſition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the old; its ſaid to be new:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of matter, or members. The old heavens were all carnall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane creatures, people for the moſt part without the knowledge of God, ſuch was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169450:16"/> the matter of the carnall Church; but the matter of this ſpirituall Church, this new heavens, ſhall be the Saints, ſuch as are all taught of God, <hi>Thy children ſhall be all righteouſneſſe.</hi> Iſa. 60. 21. Rev. 21. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. New, in oppoſition to the old man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and old converſation. The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the old Church were perhaps ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, prophane, having a form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, without the power of it; but the members of this new heaven ſhall ſo walk with God, as to honour his name, God will ſo gloriouſly appear in them, as that the world ſhal be convinced by their god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſation, <hi>The remnant that are left ſhall do no iniquity.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſhall be new, in reſpect of form, compacted together by the Spirit, not literall forms and ordinances. The old heaven, or Church-conſtitution hath been formed up with externall compactings, the wiſdom and power of the fleſh knit together by things without them, not by the bands of the Spirit, the principle and power of love, which is an everlaſting band, which will occaſion Saints commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be ſweet and ſpirituall.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169450:16"/> 4. They ſhall be new, in reſpect of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, not in the Letter, but in the Spirit, not fetcht out of the bottomleſſe pit of creature-wiſdom, and humane abilities, but the ſingle miniſtration of the Spirit; pray in the Spirit, preach and propheſie in the Spirit, praiſe in the Spirit, that is, in the wiſdom and power of that law in the Spirit, which will deliver Saints from fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actings, into the glorious liberty of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall actings, that they ſhall no more act from a legall principle, to a law without them, but from a principle of light, life, liberty, and power within them. Thus God will create a new heaven, a new Church eſtate in the Spirit, which will produce ſpirituall communion, ſpirituall joy and gladneſſe amongſt the Saints, who live in this light and glory.</p>
            <p>This that mentioned <hi>Zac.</hi> 4. 2. The candleſtick all of gold, which notes unto us the purity of the Church, not only in their comming forth of litterall Babylon, but principally of our comming forth of myſticall Babylon in theſe latter dayes; ſo likewiſe the woman cloathed with the ſun, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. having the moon under her feet; that is, the Church cloathed with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169450:17"/> Chriſt the ſun of righteouſneſſe, But unto you that fear my name, ſhall the ſun of righteouſneſſe ariſe with healing in his wings, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. with the Moon under her feet; all things be low and ſhort of Chriſt, under feet, low in eſteem with the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſoul, ſhee being with childe, travailing, pained to be delivered, that is, to bring forth Chriſt in the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>This informs us of the vanity and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thoſe, who ſeek ſo much to keep up the old Heavens, the old Church for matter and Members, that will turn the world into Church by a human power, they are thoſe that muſt be ſpiritually ſlain. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 11, 12. <hi>But ye are they that forſake the Lrod, and forget my holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that prepare a table for the troop, and furniſh a drinke offering unto that number; therefore I will number you to the ſword, and ye ſhall all bow down to the ſlaughter,</hi> &amp;c. Here is the vanity of ſuch perſons that ſeek to uphold forms, fleſhly actings, and fleſhly compactings, the old Miniſtery fetcht out of humane abilities, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh limiting the ſpirit to thoſe humane qualifications where he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears leaſt, all theſe, both perſons and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169450:17"/> things muſt bow down to the ſlaughter. Now I come to the ſecond part of my text (and a new earth) in this new Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, there is not only new heavens, but a new earth.</p>
            <p>What this new earth is, it's to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, either more myſtically or more litterally, as the new heavens. 1. Myſtically, there is an earth in the heart of every man, nay, of every chriſtian, fleſh and fleſhly corruptions, fleſhly concluſions which prevents the joy of Saints; now the Lord will make a new earth, he will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that old earth that is in his Saints, that it ſhall not ſo prevail in them, he will be a fire in them, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 3. burning up and conſuming this old earth and fleſh. O beloved there is much ignorance, even amongſt Chriſtians, of Chriſts appearing powerfully within, as a fire to burn up and conſume the deeds of darkneſſe, this is that <hi>Iohn</hi> mindes, when he ſaith he ſhall baptize you with the holy Spirit and with fire; and Chriſt himſelf, I am come to ſet fire in the earth, and what will ye if it be already kindled; truly friends it is the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169450:18"/> work of Chriſt to ſet fire in the earth, that is, that earth which is within you, as well as without you. 1. There ſhall not be ſuch earthly actings, actings after the fleſh, either the luſts of the fleſh, or the righteouſneſſe of the fleſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There ſhall not be ſuch earthly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractings, which flowe from thoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt motions and actings, but this earth being covered with the knowledge of the glory of God, and delivered from this earthlineſſe and fleſhlineſſe into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of the ſons of God, ſhall act to God more purely in the Spirit, being delivered both from fleſhly actings, and fleſhly diſtractings.</p>
            <p>Thoſe vialls of wrath mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> are not only to be poured out upon earthly perſons and things without the Saints, but likewiſe upon this earth within them, this is that minded <hi>Rev.</hi> 10 2. The Angell which is Chriſt, ſets his right foot on the ſea, and his left foot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and cried with aloud voice, and verſe 4. Seven thunders utter their voices, that is, the Lord ſpeaks a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of terror and dread to the earth and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169450:18"/> ſea, that is within the Saints, as well as without them.</p>
            <p>A Glorious word for poor Chriſtians who wait for deliverance, the viſion is for an appointed time, it will ſpeak and not lye, it will come and not, tarry, thy vile body ſhall be changed, thou ſhalt appear w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> him in glory, thou ſhalt ſee the death of that body of ſin, thou ſhalt paſſe thorow that ſea of glaſſe mingled with fire, and ſee all thy ſins, thy earthlineſſe left behinde, lying dead before thee, which will occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee to ſing new ſongs of praiſe unto the Almighty <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Comfort your ſelves with theſe things, wait, earneſtly preſſing on unto this injoyment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By earth, I underſtand to be meant 1. The powers of the earth, or the Magiſterial power, the rule &amp; government of this earth, <hi>It ſhall be an earth wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie.</hi> In what reſpect may the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtracy, or earthly powers be ſaid to be made new.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, In reſpect of the perſons ruling, they ſhall be ſuch as are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, and have an intereſt in the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God; that as formerly God hath
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169450:19"/> many times ſet up wicked men to rule and govern, ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 17. <hi>The moſt High ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth over the children of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will, and ſetteth up over it the baſeſt of men,</hi> now as God hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times given the government of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the hands of the baſeſt of men; So he will give it into the hands of the Saints.</p>
            <p>I queſtion not but that you have heard of the perſonall reign of Chriſt, that he ſhall come perſonally and ſubdue his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſo rule over the world, but this will be the glory of Chriſts kingdome, 1. He will have a glorious kingdome in the ſpirits of his people, and this is the new heavens. And 2. He will in and by his Saints rule the world.</p>
            <p>That this is a truth, I ſhall confirm unto you from Scripture. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 27. <hi>And the Kingdome and Dominion, and the greatneſſe of the Kingdome under the whole heaven, ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the most high, whoſe Kingdome is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</hi> What more myſticall truth may be in this Scripture concerning the Kingdome in the Spirit, I ſhall not queſtion, but this I beleeve to be a truth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169450:19"/> that the nations ſhall become the nations of Chriſt, and the government ſhall be in the hands of the Saints, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60 12. <hi>The Nations and Kingdomes that will not ſerve thee</hi> (to wit Chriſt in the Saints) <hi>ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; yea, thoſe nations ſhall utterly be waſted.</hi> See verſe 17, 18. <hi>For braſſe I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring ſilver, and for wood, braſſe, and for ſtones, iron,</hi> Here is the new Creation, all new: and I will make thine officers peace, and thine exactors righteouſneſſe, violence ſhall no more be heard in thy ſtreets, waſting and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction within thy borders. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30 20. <hi>Your Nobles ſhall be of your ſelves, and your Governours ſhall proceed out of the midſt of you.</hi> God will raiſe up men of ſinguler ſpirits and principles to govern the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thus, in reſpect of the perſons gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there ſhall be a new earth, for by earth is meant the earthly powers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. the earth helped the woman, that is the powers of the earth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſhall be a new earth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the manner of the perſons ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, it is a new earth, in which ſhall dwell righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. this is the great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169450:20"/> work that God hath to effect in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes of the Goſpel, to reduce Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſteriall power to its primitive inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you may ſee <hi>Rom</hi> 13. 1. <hi>There is no power but is ordained of God, and it is ordained for the puniſhment of them that do evil, but for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> Although this end hath been a long time looſed, yet now God will reduce it to this inſtitution. This is the great work right honourable that God cals for at your hands, whom he hath raiſed up for that end. See <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58. 4. <hi>Behold ye faſt for ſtrife and debate,</hi> &amp;c. verſe 6. <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to undo the heavy burdens, to let the oppreſſed go free, to break every yoke?</hi> this is a Goſpel-Faſt, and that which God cals for at your hands, it is not to hang down the head for a day like a Bull-ruſh, that ſo with more applauſe there may be a ſmiting with the fiſt of wickedneſſe; no, no beloved, it is the execution of righteouſneſſe, juſtice and mercy, without reſpect of perſons, it is to undo every yoke, and this being the great work in hand, and that which God cals for, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169450:20"/> will effect; give me leave to preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many nationall grievances, ſome few unto you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Spirituall oppreſſions in matters of conſcience. You know that a long time man hath aſſumed this power to himſelf, to rule over the conſciences of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, a great oppreſſion, and that which cannot be born in ſouls who live in light, and that from which God will deliver his people and puniſh all that oppreſſed them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In temporall oppreſſions I ſhall minde ſome few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tyranicall and oppreſſing laws, and courts of Juſtice; hence it comes to paſſe many times, that to ſeek a Remedy, proves deſtructive, the cure proves worſe then the diſeaſe; many an honeſt man chuſing rather to ſuffer loſſe, then by the uſe of meanes to ſeek his right, ſuits at law being ſo dangerous and hazerdous to the States of men; the end of law, and courts of juſtice ſhould be for the righting of men, in caſe of dammage, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, better no cure, then ſuch a cure.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Oppreſſion or grievance is in writing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169450:21"/> our lawes in an unknown tongue, that the moſt part of our Nationall inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants cannot underſtand their own lawes, that the French ſhould be better read in our Engliſh lawes, then thoſe to whom they pertain: what oppreſſion comes to the Commons of England by this means, I need not mention, its not unknown how many by this meanes are maintained by other mens loſſes.</p>
            <p>A 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Oppreſſion the kingdom grones un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is a ſlavery to the wils of men, although its that which hath been alwaies declared againſt ſince this was began, yet we never were ſo volved up into it as now, there is an affection to Arbitrarineſſe in the wills of almoſt all men, from higheſt to loweſt, men act according to their wils, whether with or againſt law, a burthen exceeding oppreſſive to this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>A 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Oppreſſion is, that of Tythes; and it is that the Kingdome, in almoſt all parts is ſenſible of it, and groans under it, with Petitions for deliverance; note,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is an oppreſſion, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away by force not only the tenth part of mens eſtate, but the tenth part of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169450:21"/> the increaſe, which is more then the fifth part of the Eſtate: Its that likewiſe which was never injoyned to be paid by any Magiſteriall power, either in Law or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but by God, and that not under a penalty neither, this was only to the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and to be paid in no land, but the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> by command.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The people groan under it as an oppreſſion, with an expectation of deliverance, witneſſe the many Petitions from many parts of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Many Saints groaning under it as a cafe of conſcience to them, yet ſuting ſo near with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> conſtitution, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a face with it, as the denying of Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>A Fifth oppreſſion, and burthen of the Kingdome, is free-quartering of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; much need there is of proviſion for ſouldiers pay, leſt the cure ſeem more heavy then the diſeaſe; leſt the work be either obſtructed, or elſe carried on with the more difficulty.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, And finally I ſay unto you as <hi>Paul</hi> in another caſe, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are of good
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169450:22"/> report &amp;c. think on thoſe things, that ſo juſtice and righteouſneſſe may flow down abundantly without reſpect of perſons; whatſoever bears but the face of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in it, let it be removed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> If this be the new earth, and the great intereſt to be followed, in a word then to conclude, how ſhould this carry on thoſe whom it concerns, who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God unto it, to the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this great work, to help forwards this great work and deſigne of God, in and by you? Note,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Policy cals for it at your hands, Right Honourable, is it not time for you to do ſomething for the Kingdome that may ingage their hearts unto you? is there not much diviſion and confuſion amongſt us, much expectation of taking away of burdens, do not the people in their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions call for it daily? truly prudent policy cals for righteouſneſſe, and undoing of burthens, that the hearts of the people may be ingaged unto you in theſe times of danger and diſtraction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Piety cals for it, it is the great
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169450:22"/> deſigne of God at preſent to exalt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and certainly God cals for it at your hands, <hi>Do juſtice, love mercy, walk humbly with thy God, Micah</hi> 6. 8. This the Lord requireth of you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Peace and ſafety cals for it, your own peace and the Kindomes peace, what is likely to produce peace in the Kingdome, if not the flowing down of righteouſneſſe and juſtice from you, the undoing of heavy burthens, and breaking of every yoke of oppreſſion? your own peace and ſafety conſiſts in it; beleeve it, there is no ſafety to be expected, if once you derogate from this great intereſt of God the publick good; you may reade in Scripture, how God poures contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Princes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 46. <hi>He poureth contempt upon Princes, and cauſeth them to wander in the wilderneſſe, where there is no way.</hi> Hath not God poured contempt upon many princes already, when once they derogate from that publick intereſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by them, ſeeking their own ends? does not God poure contempt upon them? and be you aſſured whom God hath called to this great work, if once you
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169450:23"/> turn aſide from the publike to your own private intereſts, God will poure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon you. This being a truth of God, I ſhall at preſent conclude with that Scripture <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. the 6 and the 8 verſes. <hi>If you looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do the heavy burdens, and let the oppreſſed go free, and break every yoke,</hi> Then verſe 8. <hi>Shall thy light break forth as the morning, and thy health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily, and thy righteouſneſſe ſhall go before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be thy rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> Here is light, here is peace, here is ſafety: thy righteouſneſſe ſhall go before thee, that is, God in Chriſt, and the ſame glory ſhall be your rear-ward. So much for preſent.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
